ANDREl RUBLEV
Pull the rope.
This is one?
Arkhip, give me the strap.
Hold it.
Take it.
Look!
lt's Yefim, isn't it?
Come here and help.
Pull the rope.
Hold on a second.
Come on, quick!
Where is it?
Here.
Come on, fast.
Lift it.
-Lord. Let it go right.
-Untie it now.
The rope is tangled.
Hold it!
We won't have enough time.
l'm ready!
Archipushka! You try to
hold them!
Just a second.
Come on!
Hold him, hold him!
l'm here. l'm here.
Cut the rope, man!
Cut the rope!
l'll show you, cut the rope!
My God!
Yefim!
Where are you going?
Archipushka!
l'm flying! l'm flying!
Hey! Chase me! Chase me!
My God! What is it?
Archipushka!
THE JESTER
Summer 140O
Danil!
Danil! The father told you
to go back!
There is no one to paint
the icons.
For God's sake!
lt's no business of yours.
You will be sorry for that. You will
come begging on your knee's.
Come on. You never know.
We shall see.
lt's not good.
What?
That we are leaving Troitsa.
lt's a shame.
Aren't there enough painters in
Moscow without us, Danil?
We'll find some sort of work.
All this is right, but it's
a pity that...
l passed this birch every day
and never noticed it.
When you know you'll never see
it, again means something.
lt's been ten years. Nine for
you, but ten for me.
No, seven for me
nine for you.
-lt's raining.
-Come on here.
Let's go. We will not melt.
The jesters were walking. Drunk
on mead and beer...
when they met their master,
the Boyar...
and they sang, to greet him:
O master. O Boyar...
everything is ready in
the kitchen!
The Boyar's plump wife
is a choosy trollop.
Mistress, open the door.
The master's coming!
The Boyar yells: ''Jesters are all
thieves and drunkards!''
''You should be whipped from
Friday to Friday!''
''You goats and tramps, drown
in your beer!''
''Soon you will be impaled!''
The Jesters grabbed him between
his navel and his knees.
They shaved his beard; what's a
Boyar without his beard?
Any woman would rather
he had a beard.
The Boyar yells, hops
about like a flea.
He scurries home, raps
on the window.
But his wife doesn't recognize
his naked cheeks...
with no beard to grab hold of.
She whacked him with
a rolling pin.
What a disgrace!
''Cover your naked cheeks
with your breeches.''
''Clear off, beardless Boyar!''
He hobbled off, pursued
by geese...
and meet a priest...
who mistook him for a woman and
dragged him into the bushes.
Without breeches...
he looks the same at each end.
The woman saw a naked head...
and grabbed it by the beard.
May we shelter from the storm?
Come in.
Do you want some beer?
You are soaking wet.
Thank you, we don't imbibe.
And don't play around with women.
God sent priests, but the
devil sent jesters.
The woman saw a head!
By the beard!
My woman might have been
playing in the bushes.
l'll show you!
Come here, you.
What are you doing?
Give it back to him.
Where were you, Kirill?
Outside. Shall we go?
Danil, the rain's stopped;
Iet's go.
Christ be with you, mistress.
THEOPHANES THE GREEK
Summer-Winter-Spring-Summer-1405-1406
l'm innocent!
Let me go!
ls anyone in here?
Have you come to look?
Yes, to look.
Then look. We'll soon be finished.
So you are Theophanes the Greek?
Why look at me? Look there.
Where are you from?
From Andronnikov Monastery.
From Andronnikov Monastery? Are you
by chance Andrei Rublev?
No.
l've heard everyone praise
this Rublev.
He's good, but not as good as this.
Such delicate colors.
Oh Lord, it's just...
Why did you stop praising me?
Go on.
l can't. l can't find the
right words.
Konstantin Kostechevsky was
right when he said:
''Only with true insight...
can you grasp its essence.''
Whereas Andrei... and l'll
tell him to his face...
He's like my brother.
He's praised, it's true: he paints
well. With subtlety.
But there's something Lacking
in all his work.
There's no awe, no faith...
no faith that comes from the
depths of his soul.
No simplicity.
As Epiphanius said in ''The Life of
Saint Sergeius'':
''Simplicity, without gaudiness.''
That is what this is. It's sacred.
Simplicity, without gaudiness...
you can't say it better.
l see you are a wise man.
lf so, is that a good thing?
lf one is ignorant, isn't it better
to be guided by one's heart?
ln much wisdom there
is much grief...
And he who increases knowledge
increases sorrow.
Proshka! Where is that oil?
Whose ears should l box?
lt is as though the earth has
swallowed everyone.
They say you paint quickly.
l cannot work any other way.
l got bored.
l wasted a week on an icon once.
You threw it away?
No. l used the board to
press cabbage.
lt's all so boring.
l have pupils and assistants
in abundance...
But none of them is any good.
They can neither red nor write.
Listen, help me. Be my assistant.
Don't make fun of me.
l'm not making fun of you.
ln spring, l must paint the Church of
the Annunciation in Moscow...
and l have no assistants
to do it with.
The scaffolding is being built.
-Do you understand?
-l do understand.
But l wouldn't be able to cope.
l'll teach you. You never prepared
a wall for a fresco?
You've a brain; even these idiots
can prepare a wall.
l said no and l mean no.
You know best...
But mind you don't regret;
l am rancorous.
l may regret it, but it's
a sin for you.
An unknown monk comes to you...
and you like the fact that you can
talk about books with him...
and you decide to take him
and favor him.
But l haven't looked at a book for
three years and l don't want to.
-Why?
-l have a different road.
Wicked bastards!
Where is Proshka?
Where is Vikenty?
They ran to the square to see how
they were going to kill the ruler.
Wicked bastards!
See?
And you don't want to help?
-l shall die soon.
-You shouldn't say that.
The other night l dreamed
of an angel.
He said: ''Come with me.''
l said: ''l shall die soon
without you.''
You won't change your mind,
will you?
Only on one condition.
Whatever you want. Money?
Half my fee, okay?
No. l'll work for nothing if
you yourself...
Come to Andronnikov Monastery
to fetch me.
Before the community, the
metropolitan, ask me to help you...
Before the brotherhood
before Andrei Rublev.
Then l shall serve you
like a slave...
Like a dog, until the day l die.
What is your name?
Kirill.
Orthodox Christians
Iovers of truth.
How long will this torture go on,
when will...
you end this?
You are thoughtless sinners,
yet you judge.
You faithless heathens!
He has already seven times
atoned for his sins...
for both his sins and yours.
You are incredible
sinners yourselves.
And you judge... but you don't
have God with you.
Rejoice, o young man,
in thy youth...
and let thy heart cheer thee
in the days of thy youth.
Walk in the ways of the thine heart,
an in the sight of thine eyes...
but know that for all these...
God will bring thee into judgment.
Remember now thy Creator in
the days of thy youth...
before the difficult days come...
and the years draw nigh, when
thou shalt say...
''l have no pleasure in them.''
Remember thy Creator...
before the silver cord be loosed. Or
the golden bowl be broken...
or the pitcher shattered
at the fountain...
or the wheel broken at the well.
Then shall the dust return to the
earth as it was...
and the spirit shall return unto
God who gave it.
''Vanity of vanities,'' saith the
preacher; ''All is vanity.''
Kirill, have you seen
Father Nikodim?
Where has he got to since
this morning?
He took my gloves, then disappeared
as though the earth swallowed
l have to chop wood and
the logs are icy.
Why is your candle burning?
It's daylight.
Did you feed my dog?
Did you ask me to?
What's the matter with you?
Go away.
The words of the wise are like
goads, and the words of...
scholars are like well-driven nails
given by one Shepherd.
And further, my son, you should
stay away from these.
N making many books
there is no end...
and much study is wearisome
to the flesh.
Let us hear the conclusion of
the whole matter...
Fear God and keep His
commandments...
for this is man's all.
A messenger has come!
Who has come? A messenger from
Moscow has come.
A messenger has come from
the Grand Prince.
So?
So so.
A messenger from Theophanes
the Greek.
The Grand Prince orders
you to Moscow...
To paint the cathedral of the
Annunciation, with Theophanes.
ls he really Andrei Rublev,
this fellow?
Yes, he's Rublev... and l'm Kirill.
Theophanes the Greek says he
wants you in Moscow...
and he wishes to see you.
l thank Theophanes.
Tell him...
that l'll come.
l'll come.
My head is splitting!
Bring my horse here.
What is wrong?
Choose whichever helpers you like
and be ready tomorrow.
,
Is there a blacksmith here? If not
l'll fall off again.
There is a smithy outside,
beyond the chapel.
Farewell, God-fearing people!
Semyon! Come here!
Come here and help us!
Why are you standing?
Come here!
Let's go today, shall we,
Danil?
Go quickly, before Theophanes
changes his mind.
l'm not going.
Why aren't you going?
How can l manage without you?
As best you can.
l thought we'd go together.
Why did you think for me?
l was not invited.
l can't do it without you.
You can; you agreed to go
without asking me.
Theophanes simply beckoned.
Don't grieve; you're not
the first, or the last.
Even without you there's plenty
of work for me here.
Thank God for it.
Foma, Aleksei. Let's get ready.
Piotr, you're coming with me.
Did you forget something, Andrei?
l came to say farewell.
We've said farewell.
l came to say farewell, but...
it was hard for me before.
Then the devil created enmity
bettween us.
l can't go away like this.
l must make confession.
Will you hear it?
l cannot do anything, Danil...
After living so many years together
in the same cell.
Apart from you, l have on one.
l see the world with your eyes.
l hear it with your ears...
With your heart.
l am happy for you, you old fool.
lf only knew how happy.
Go to Moscow. Paint; l shall
be proud of you.
The devil tempted me the other
day too. Forgive me.
l'll come back, Danil.
Where are you going? What
about Vespers?
l'll manage without you.
What's wrong with you today,
Kirill?
l'm tired of lying. l'm going back
into the secular world.
Why did we leave the
Trinity Monastery?
Andrei, Danil, you are not
saying anything.
Because the brothers valued profit
higher than faith.
They forgot why they had entered
a monastery.
And now?
We sought to praise God with faith
and work, but what's happened?
The monastery's become a bazaar.
Servant of god, how many souls did
you trade in for monasticism?
Twenty or thirty?
And you ran after the Father
Superior, bargaining.
For ttwo meadows, or even one, you
bought eternal salvation.
You don't need me to tell you, but
you prefer to keep quiet.
Perhaps l would also tolerate all
this loathsomeness if l had talent.
But what talent? Just a slight
ability to paint icons.
God be praised that He
gave me no talent.
l'm happy l'm untalented; l can be
honest and pure before god.
You are taking sin upon
your soul!
l'll tell you something else,
brothers.
What to you want to tell us that
we don't l know already?
Do you know what happens to
your sort? Speak!
l won't get offended!
Well, l...
Get out, you dog!
Out of my sight, you serpent! Rejoin
the secular world, slanderer!
Now do you see?
Kirill!
lt is written: ''And Jesus went into
the temple of God...
and cast out all them that sold
and bought in the temple...
and overthrew the tables of
the money changers...
and the seats of them that
sold doves.''
,
''And said unto them,'' it is written
''My house shall be called...
the house of prayer; but ye have
made it a den of thieves.''
For three years l was cleaning
brushes for Danil...
Before he let me touch an icon.
And then only to clean it.
Don't you trust me?
You're always lying, Foma.
Yesterday your robe was sticky;
where were you?
At the beehive.
But you said you were at
the monastery.
Just look at yourself.
Put mud or something
on your cheek....
Or you will swell, like a hog.
lt's too late now, it's useless.
You're constantly making
up stories.
l even think you have a disease.
Me? What disease?
There is a disease where a man
lies without stopping.
Look, Foma.
Look, l say.
What?
You think know everything so l'm not
going to teach you any more.
Why should l learn?
Anyway, l will have to spend three
years cleaning the brushes.
l'm sick and tired of you,
Foma.
Go back to the monastery, go
wherever you want.
l can't understand why l took
you as a pupil.
You are always like that. First you
say one thing then another.
You yourself told Theophanes
l was perceptive.
You were different then; you
worked, you didn't lie.
And do you know what
Theophanes said?
''What does it matter it
he's perceptive?''
Whatever Theophanes has said...
l can see blue colors better
than anyone else.
You eat too much; how can you paint
with a bloated stomach?
When your stomach's rumbling, how
can your mind work?
The rumbling is the only
sound you hear.
You're lucky, Foma. For you,
everything is simple.
lf you are not painting, you are
sleeping or fooling around.
But only by prayer can the soul
transcend the flesh.
Would you go to learn from another
teacher instead of me?
Why not, it you tell me to go?
Come on, come on.
Don't be angry.
What's that?
So you've decided to put the
apostle on the left, Andrei.
Did you take glue off the fire?
Perceptive is he?
He should be beaten every
Saturday, like a dog.
You're obstinate, Andrei.
How did you so much? Everyone else
is thinking only of himself.
l say it, Theophanes.
The women of Moscow gave their
hair to the Tatars.
What else could the poor
creatures do?
Better to lose their hair than be
tortured. Is that heroic?
lt is.
lt is true that Russian women are
humiliated and unhappy.
lt's not what l mean.
Tell me honestly, are the people
ignorant or not?
Well, are they?
They're ignorant, but whose
fault is that?
lt's their own stupidity. Have you
never sinned through ignorance?
Everyone has.
And l have too. God forgive us
and make us better.
Well, never mind.
The Last Judgment is coming;
we'll burn like candles.
Mark my words.
Each will accuse the other of his
own sins, to defend himself.
Theophanes, how can you paint with
such ideas, even accept praise?
l have become a hermit and
lived in a cave.
l serve God, not man.
As regards praise, what is praised
today is abused tomorrow.
They will forget you, me,
everything.
All is vanity and ashes. Worse
things have been forgotten.
Humanity has already committed
every stupidity and baseness....
and now it only repeats them.
Everything is an eternal circle and
it repeats and repeats itself.
lf Jesus returned to earth, they
would crucify him again.
N course, if only evil
is remembered....
then you will never be happy in
the sight of God.
Perhaps we must forget some
things; but not all.
l don't know how to say it.
Then be quiet and listen to me.
So.
You think that one can only
do good alone?
Good. Remember the
New Testament.
Jesus taught people
in the temples...
so why did they gather later?
To kill him!
''Crucify him'' they shouted.
And the disciples? Judas sold Him.
Peter denied Him.
They all ran away, yet they
were the best.
But they repented.
That was afterwards, when
it was too late.
lt's never too late to repent.
N course, people do evil.
But you can not blame
them altogether.
lt's difficult...
and sinful, l think.
Judas sold the Christ, and remember
who bought him.
People.
And who accused Jesus?
The scribes and Pharisees...
they could not find witnesses,
however hard they tried.
''Who will testify against
this innocent?''
Only later on they found
the traitors.
Two were found immediately.
Two, and not one.
There were only ttwo.
The Pharisees were masters
of deceit, educated.
They had studied to gain power...
to take advantage of the
people's ignorance.
We must remind people more often
that they are people.
,
Russians, of the same blood
of the same land.
Evil is everywhere.
Someone will always sell you for
thirty pieces of silver.
New misfortunes constantly
befall the peasant...
either Tatars three times an
autumn, or famine, or plague...
and he still keeps on working,
working, working...
meekly bearing his cross.
He does not despair, he is
silent and patient.
He only prays to God for
enough strength.
How could god not forgive
him his ignorance?
You know yourself. You're
tired and discouraged...
and suddenly...
in the crowd you meet a
human glance...
and everything's lighter, as it
is after Communion.
lsn't it so?
You just spoke of Jesus.
Perhaps He was born and
crucified to reconcile...
God and man.
Jesus came from God, so
He is all-powerful.
,
And if He died on the cross
it was predetermined...
and His crucifiKion and death
were God's will.
That would have aroused hatred
not in those who crucified Him...
but in those who loved Him...
if they had been near Him
at that moment...
because they loved Him
as a man only.
,
but if He, of His own will
Ieft them...
He displayed injustice,
or even cruelty.
Maybe those who crucified
Him loved Him...
because they helped in
this divine plan.
Do you understand what you
are saying?
They'll exile you to the
north, man, to renovate the icons.
Am l not right? You too always
say what you think.
But l'm not a monk; l'm free.
THE HOLIDAY
spring 1408
Sergei, over here!
Foma, let's get some logs.
Piotr as probably never seen either
Assumption Cathedral so...
Saint Dimitry Cathedral.
Never mind, he will begin working,
and understand things.
Foma Where are you?
We don't be on time.
lt's okay, we'll be there tomorrow.
No. We'll never finish the Cathedral
of the Assumption by winter.
lt's almost June, Andrei.
What is it?
Quiet! Do you hear it?
Nightingales?
Nothing else?
Come on.
-What is it?
-Come on.
They're practicing witchcraft.
Where are you going?
Come to me.
Hold on.
Darling.
Take your hand away.
There is an anthill.
Anthill?
Anthill.
Who is this?
l don't know.
Let's go.
lt seemed to me as if a black
snake was hiding himself.
What are you doing?
Let me go!
We'll let you go.
At dawn, we'll hang a stone around
your neck, to help you swim.
Heaven's fire will consume you!
The Last Judgment awaits!
Now we'll tie you to this cross
like Jesus Christ.
No!
What are you doing, men?
You can't to this to me.
This is a sin. At least hang
me upside-down.
Men, brothers!
Leave him here for the night,
unless he ascends again.
He's not going anywhere.
And who is this?
Marfa.
Why did you want to be head down?
It would have been worse.
Why did you threaten us with
fire from heaven?
lt is a sin to go naked and
do what you do.
What sin? Tonight is for
Iovemaking; is love a sin?
ls it to tie a man up like this?
You might call the monks...
who would force us to
accept your faith.
Do you think it's easy
to live in fear?
You live in fear because
you know no...
love but bestial love.
Carnality without soul; but love
should be brotherly.
lsn't all love the same?
It's just love.
What are you doing?
Untie me.
Why are you looking at me?
Where were you?
Thank God.
Are these the people?
No, these are strangers.
Don't you see it?
,
There is some onion
if you want it.
Where were you?
These forests are impenetrable;
l'm all scratched.
The local people like it. They are
accustomed to it.
For people, everything is a
matter of custom.
Old people don't need to think...
for their days pass according
to custom.
But perhaps they consciously
enjoy...
the way the days drag on.
Couldn't you get here before?
No. l couldn't.
That is your sin, your conscience,
your prayers.
Get him, and her!
Why are they doing that?
Because the accursed pagans don't
believe in one God.
Don't look, Sergei. There is
nothing to look at.
Let me go!
You can't see that!
Kich so he shuts up!
Go, go! Don't dawdle!
Help, Fyodor! Help!
Fyodor!
Can't you deal with a woman?
Stop!
Hold her!
Marfa, run!
Catch her!
-Where are you going?
-She will drown herself!
Marfa! Run, Marfa!
Swim, Marfa!
THE LAST JUDGMENT
Summer 1408
Come here!
He's just wasting materials.
Who needs it?
Foma!
What do you want?
Can l go for a swim?
No, you can't.
lt's hot!
Don't be lying. It's not.
Maybe he's really hot.
l'm hot too.
N course, you are working
and he is sitting.
Let him go swim.
Don't spoil him.
Let him be sitting with everyone.
You shut up!
You sleep all day long like a log...
and you come down only to eat
and go to the bathroom.
And have you found a job for me?
-You have found what you wanted.
-So what?
Since everyone is sitting here, let
Serezhka be sitting with us to.
lf you had let him go, he would
have been back already.
Give him freedom...
and he will in the water until
he turns blue.
He only thinks that it's hot...
-and that's why he is whining.
-He's not whining,...
you are.
lt was me.
l was the first to say it's hot,
and not Sergei.
Why are you picking on Sergei?
That's it!
You want to go swimming, go!
Go! Why are you sitting?
Go, go!
Here! You see?
Wait! Wait!
Where's Andrei?
Not here?
Not here? This is a fine
state of affairs.
l was our bishop's house
just now.
Such a fuss. Yelling!
He was purple with rage. ''l've
Iost patience!'' He cried.
He meant you. All of you.
,
''For two whole months,'' he said
everything has been ready.
But they haven't started yet.
Nothing is ready; they asked for
so much money, but do nothing.
None of them is working and
nothing is ready.''
Did you ask for a lot of money?
How do l know?
He said, ''l don't care. Danil
Chorny or Andrei Rublev...
it's all the same to me.''
''lt's all the same.''
And he pulled a face like this.
''What do l care about
Andrei Rublev?
By autumn,'' he says...
''l want the cathedral painted,
and that's that!''
He's sent a courier with a complaint
to the Grand Prince.
He's sent a courier to the
Grand Prince.
lt's a complaint about you,
you know.
You haven't started yet.
You'd better hurry up.
Where's Andrei?
He's gone somewhere again.
Can't you start without him?
Go on, start without him.
Why are you smirking? There
are so many of you.
lf he can't make his mind up,
can't one of you?
Two heads are better than one.
Where is Andrei?
l can't go on like that.
Answer me: yes or no?
Yes or no? Wasn't everything
decided in Moscow?
To the smallest detail; the Prince
said everything was in order.
What is not clear? What have we
been discussing for two months?
Explain it to me. l may be old,
l may have lost my wits.
The Last Judgment; either you
accept the task and paint it...
or you refuse the commission.
And if we really refused? If we
went back, Danil?
How shall l face people?
l should die of shame.
We're wasting such good time.
This heat, no rain.
We could have finished the cupola
and the columns.
How wonderfully they could
have been done...
how brightly, and beautifully.
On the right sinners...
boiling in pitch, painted to make
your flesh crawl.
l have thought of a great devil, with
smoke from his nose and eyes.
-lt's not the smoke that matters.
-Then what matters?
l don't know.
-Why aren't you looking at me?
-Because l can't.
l can't paint all that;
it disgusts me.
l don't want to terrify people.
Understand me, Danil.
Collect yourself! Listen!
lt's the Last judgment!
l didn't invent it.
l can't do it. Do as you will,
but l can't.
Why didn't you speak earlier,
in Moscow?
You shouldn't have agreed.
This is dishonest.
l am what l am. You couldn't
teach me integrity.
l don't know what to paint.
What do you mean,
you don't know?
We were ordered to paint the
Last Judgment.
You see...
l think it will be better...
if we don't paint the Last
Judgment at all.
What do you mean?
You know.
l want...
l don't want anything.
-Nothing.
-That's it.
Well, l leaving.
This is no work for me.
Thanks for you kindness and your
slaps; l learned something.
But now l'm going to work
for myself.
They've asked me to paint a
church at Pafnutievo.
Not a great honor, but it's
still an honor.
l'm going to paint the
Last Judgment.
Who will come with me?
Well, then, stay...
But don't complain later.
When l was a child...
l speak as a child, l understood as
a child, l thought as a child...
but when l became a man,...
l put away childish things.
For now we see through
a glass, darkly...
but then face to face
now l know in part...
but then shall l know...
even as also l am know.
And now abideth...
faith, hope, and charity...
but the greatest of these
is charity.
Though l speak with the tongues
of men and of angels...
and have not charity...
l am become as sounding brass,
or a tinkling cymbal.
And though l have the
gift of prophecy...
and understand all mysteries,
and all knowledge...
and though l have all faith, so that
l could remove mountains...
and have not charity,
l am nothing.
And though l bestow all my
goods to feed the poor...
and thought l give my body to be
burned, and have not charity...
it profiteth me nothing.
Charity suffereth long, and is kind;
charity envieth not...
charity vaunteth not itself, is
not puffed up...
doth not behave itself unseemly...
seeketh not her own, is not
easily provoked,...
thinketh no evil.
rejoiceth not in iniquity, but
rejoiceth in the truth...
beareth all things...
believeth all things, hopeth
all things,...
endureth all things.
Charity never faileth...
but whether there be prophecies,
they shall fail...
whether there be tongues,
they shall cease...
whether there be knowledge,
it shall vanish away.
For we know in part...
Princess, is that nice?
lt's sinful to splash milk.
Such a naughtiness.
Why is it sinful?
Because...wipe it off.
But it will dry by itself
in a minute.
Let's walk by the stream.
Let me go, Stepan, or l'll send
you to the stables.
How do you like it? l couldn't imagine
it better. It's light, beautiful.
lt's light.
Take her out. Her nurses
have spoiled her.
l say!
No one can build a mansion
better than us.
Who could paint like that?
Only Mitiai can do this directly,
without tracing.
lt's like a bird singind.
Look. Maybe it is like a
bird singind.
l don't care. l can sleep on the hay.
You are the Grand Prince.
Don't you like it?
l'll tell you this. It should
be repainted.
Walls, ceiling, everything:
brighter, stronger colors.
l've been in this trade for
forty years.
lt's not the years that matter...
but your ability to glorify the
Grand Prince with your work.
That's enough. Go.
We won't redo anything.
lt's time to go. We
have another job.
They are waiting for us
in Zvenigorod.
Where?
At your brother's. They have
the stone already.
A beautiful stone. Whiter
than this.
When your brother came
at Easter...
we made a deal and he said: ''Do what
you like, whatever the cost.
l'll tax the peasants more,
just build me the...''
best mansion possible.
Then go to Zvenigorod.
Stepan!
Here, l have brought it.
,
When l looked at the Prince
be become numb.
-When l mentioned Zvenigorod?
-Yes, he became paralyzed.
He fears his brother will
outshine him.
Who carved that?
l did.
Why didn't you set in the wall?
lt didn't come out right.
Pity; It's rather good.
Everything crumbles: l told the Prince
to spare no expense on the stone.
Maybe now he's sorry when he
heard about Zvenigorod.
l could have carved beautiful
things for him.
Come on, you ass!
Where's Stepan?
Where did Stepan gallop to?
He went Zvenigorod
with others.
l've dirtied my hands.
We'll build another mansion
just as good for the...
Prince's brother.
Will the stone be better there?
Yes, it will.
Look, the Captain of the Guard.
Hold on, old man.
You, ass! Help him! In the bushes!
Where's my whip?
Has anyone seen my whip?
Damn. l've lost it. Have you
seen my whip, ass?
Seryoga.
What?
Read the Scriptures.
From where?
From wherever you like.
''lmitate me, just as l also
imitate Christ.
Now l praise you, brethren, that ye
remember me in all things...
and keep the ordinances as
l delivered them to you.
But l would have you know, that the
head of every man is Christ...
and the head of the woman
is the man...
and the head of Christ is God.
Every man praying or prophesying,
having his head covered...
dishonoreth his head. But every
woman that prayeth...
or prophesieth...
,
with her head uncovered
dishonoreth her head...
for that is even all one as if
she were shaven.
,
For if the woman be not covered
Iet her also be shorn...
but if it be shame for a woman
to be shorn or shaven...
let her be covered.
For a man ought not to cover
his head...
forasmuch as he is the image
and glory of God...
but the woman is the glory
of the man.
For the man is not of the woman;
but the woman of the man.
Neither was the man created for
the woman; but the...
woman for the man.
For this cause ought the woman to
have power on her head...
because of the angels.
Nevertheless neither is the man
without the woman...
neither the woman without the
man, in the Lord.''
Go on reading.
,
''For as the woman is of the man
even so is, even so is the man...
also by the woman; but all
things of God.
Judge in yourselves: is it comely...
that a woman pray unto
God uncovered?
Doth not even nature itself teach
you that, if a man have...
long hair it is a shame unto him?
But if a woman have long hair,...
it is a glory to her for her
hair is given her for...
Why have you stopped? Read.
But if a woman have long hair,
it is a glory for her...
But if any man seen to
be contentious...
we have no such custom
neither the Churches of God.
Now in this that l declare unto you
l praise you not...
that ye come together not for the
better but for the worse.
Danil ,listen.
lt's a feast.
lt's a feast, Danil, and
you are saying...
They are not sinners...
She is not a sinner, even if she
dose not a wear a scarf.
She is not a sinner.
Leave him alone. Let God's
servant repent.
THE PASSlON
According to Andrei Part Two.
THE RAID
Autumn of 1408
They are coming! The Tatars
are coming, Prince!
Hey, Prince! Is this your ford?
lt has been raining, and everything
is flooded. Follow us.
We were just going to leave. We
expected you yesterday.
l couldn't resist attacking a small
town on my way.
l am sorry l am late.
Never mind. Let's go. It will be
shallow to the left.
Keep to the left.
This isn't a trap?
Believe me, Vladimir is deserted.
My brother, the Grand Prince,
is in Lithuania.
Here is the town, behind
that forest.
They say the Prince has a son,
but you want the throne.
We'll see.
l see you want the throne.
l understand.
You were told to keep left.
Grab this!
Come on, Prince! Don't lag behind!
Strong is your love for your brother.
This is our destiny.
When were you last reconciled
with him?
l never was. The Metropolitan
summoned us...
and made us kiss the cross and
swear to live in harmony.
What are you saying?
The Metropolitan summoned us to
kiss the cross.
-When?
-Last winter.
Vladimir is a beautiful town.
Do you like it?
Yes.
Let's go.
Forward! You dog, stay close,
or l'll kill you!
Keep close to the Prince!
To the gates!
Let's go.
Tatars!
Run away!
What is going on?
The Grand Prince is coming.
The brother has arrived.
Hold him, hold him!
Brothers, what are you doing?
We Are all fellow Russians.
l'll show you if we are fellow
Russians, you Vladimir swine
Catch him! Catch him!
Run around! Don't you hear me?
Where the devil are we?
There's no one here.
They've all fled.
How your bitch has grown; doesn't
remember me, eh?
Vaska, take the dog.
Oh please, let me go!
Don't be afraid, beautiful.
l'll show you how Tatars can love.
Well, Prince!
Aren't you sorry about
the cathedral?
Tell me Prince, who is that woman?
lt's no woman, the Virgin Mary:
the Nativity.
Who is in the box?
Christ, her son.
How can she be a virgin if
she has a son?
Strange things happen in Russia!
Very interesting.
Tie his legs tighter!
Tell the truth, you dog!
Hold on, hold on! l haven't
seen your gold.
By God, by God, l haven't seen it!
lt hurts!
l don't know where the gold is;
it probably was stolen.
Your Tatars must have taken it.
You're all thieves.
Ask around your own men.
He hasn't told the truth.
Come here, l'll tell you
something.
See how the devils torture an
innocent Russian believer.
Look you Judas,
you dirty Tatar!
You lie, l'm Russian.
l recognize you. You resemble
your brother.
You've sold Russia!
l recognized you!
Mark may words!
''No Tatar shall ever set foot
on Russian soil.''
This is my vow to the Lord.
Give me a cross. Let a believer
kiss the cross.
You'll get your cross.
lf l have sinned, may God forgive.
God is merciful.
Lord, will you pardon me?
But all you will boil in pitch.
You will leave and we will
rebuild again...
but your guts will go to
the fires of hell.
What are you doing this for?
Theophanes? Bur you are dead.
l want to see you so much.
Even if you had not wanted, l would
have come anyway.
l dreamed you were suspended in a
window with your head down.
You look in, and wag your
finger at me...
and l'm lying across a saddle...
and two Tatars twist my head.
And you look at me, and tap
on the window.
Toc... toc...
And l cry out to you.
What do you cry?
What's happening to us?
We are being murdered and raped.
Together with Tatars, they are
pillaging churches.
And you said to me...
Only now l'm worse off than you.
You're dead, but l...
Dead? What of it?
l didn't mean that.
l've spent half my life
in blindness.
l worked for people day
and night.
But they aren't people,
are they?
What you said was true.
So what if l said it then?
You are wrong now, l was
wrong then.
But haven't we the same faith...
the same land...
the same blood?
One Tatar even smiled.
Like this!
And shouted:
''Even without us you'll cut each
other's throats!''
What a disgrace.
They killed everyone.
Even my Seryoga.
l found him on such a special day.
She is the only one that survived.
lt's time for me to go.
Wait.
Don't go. Don't you like being
with me; are you bored?
All right, l won't...
Let's sit and talk. l'll tell you...
But l already know everything.
Then you know l'll never paint again.
Why so?
Because it's of no use to anyone.
That's all.
So what? Your iconostasis
was burned.
Do you know how many of mine they
burned? In Pskov, Novgorod...
You are committing a grave sin.
l haven't told you the worst.
l killed a man.
A fellow Russian.
When l saw him carrying her off.
Look at her.
Just look at her!
l don't remember how it happened.
l caught up with him...
and l couldn't help it.
Through our sins, evil has
assumed human form.
Encroaching evil means
encroaching humanity.
God will forgive you; don't
forgive yourself.
Live, between divine forgiveness
and your own torment.
As for your sins, what do your
scriptures say?
''Learn to do good: seek justice...
rebuke the oppressor, defend the
fatherless, plead for the widow.
Come now, and let us reason
together, saith the Lord...
thought your sins be as scarlet...
they shall be as white as snow.''
See, l haven't forgotten; that
may comfort you.
l know, God is merciful and
will pardon me.
l shall offer the Lord
vow of silence.
l have nothing more to
say to people.
ls this a good idea?
l have no right to advise you.
Didn't you go to heaven?
Lord!
l can only say it is not as you
imagine it on earth.
Russia, Russia
Our mother country suffers all;
she will endure all.
But how long will this go on?
,
l don't know. Forever
most likely.
Yet how beautiful all this is.
lt's snowing.
Nothing is more terrible than snow
falling in a temple.
THE CHARITY
Winter 1412
The apples are all rotten.
ln all my years, l've never seen
such a famine.
We are slowly dying out.
Lord have pity on us.
Mefody is bringing someone again.
Mefody, you should not be
the gate-keeper...
because you will let the people the
whole neighborhood in here to eat.
-Sit down, man of God.
-Thank you.
To eat!
You can't feed all the
hungry people.
There is no one in the
neighborhood.
The villages are deserted.
Everyone has left Khotkovo.
The people of Semyonovka
have fled.
They've fled, they've fled!
lt's true. l passed Semyonovka
this morning.
ln Vladimir it is even worse.
No harvest for three years;
everyone has fled.
Those who stayed are eating mice.
Why are you whispering?
l'm not whispering. l have a cold.
l spent a night in a lake.
Why was that?
,
Wolves chased me; l fled to the lake
praying they wouldn't follow.
l was starting like that till dawn.
When l got out, l was
completely numb.
l've been sick for two weeks and
l'm shivering all over.
-So you're from Vladimir.
-So used to live there.
Someone else from
Vladimir is here.
Andrei Rublev. Here you
heard of him?
He has sinned, and now
he is atoning.
He has brought a holy fool with
him from Vladimir.
A mute girl.
Now they are silent together.
Though she is a holy fool, she
knows where to...
get better food.
He has brought her...
so that he may always
remember his sin.
Can you call it holiness?
And Rublev's guild?
lt fell apart.
Some were killed by Tatars...
others were driven away.
ls Danil alive?
Some say he went north,
others say he died.
So he's given up his craft?
Aren't you Kirill?
Kirill, is it you?
Father! Master! Kirill has
come back!
Father! Let your prodigal son
Kirill back in!
You didn't ask me if you
could leave...
and now you want to come back?
You didn't like it in the
secular world?
No, l won't take you in.
My God, why hast thou
forsaken me?
Now you want back into the
den of thieves...
to the money-changers
and dove-sellers.
You think because l am old, l have
forgotten about it.
Begone! Go back to where
you came from!
There is no truth in the world.
The devil tempted me.
l can't continue sinning...
and without sin you cannot live
in the secular world.
There is sin and dirt all around.
Accept my penitence and l will
kiss your feet.
You were always eloquent, but
you won't move me, Kirill.
lf you knew how l've suffered,
what l've endured...
if you knew what evil l've seen,
you would forgive me...
but l will never forgive myself.
You're not guilty before me,
but before God.
Remain here; but to
eKpiate your sin...
you must copy out the Scriptures
fifteen times.
Take the late Nikodim's cell.
Thank you! Thank you, God!
How wonderful! Thank you,
father, thank you!
Hey, it's bad to eat dirty meat.
Brothers, what's going on?
l'll go to tell Father Nikodim.
A good Russian. She eats
horsemeat.
Do you want to come with me?
You'll be my wife.
l have seven wives, but no
Russian wife.
You will eat horsemeat every
day, drink horse milk,...
wear coins in hair.
Russian wife for Tatar
husband is never dirty.
Girl! Come with us!
Come! Give me your hand!
Do you hear me, Andrei?
Don't you recognize me?
Don't grieve, they'll her go.
They won't dare harm a holy
fool. It's a sin.
THE BELL Spring-Summer-Autumn
Winter-Spring 1423-1424
,
Is this the home of Nikolka
the bell-maker?
lt is.
ls he your father?
Yes.
Then call him.
-He's not here.
-Where is he?
He's dead.
The plague took them all:
mother, sister, father.
And where does Gravrila the
bell-maker live?
Gravrila? He's dead, too.
So is Kasian, and the Tatars led
Ivashka away last year.
Only Fyodor is left. Go to
him; the fifth hut.
But you should hurry; Fyodor's
in bed with the plague.
He can't open his eyes. He will
pass away at any moment.
l can't stand it any more. Where
else can we look? Let's go home.
Get up. You aren't going home.
ls there no one left to
cast the bell?
Take me with you.
Let me cast the bell for you.
Are you mad, boy?
Take to the Prince.
Honestly, l can make everything
very well for you.
You won't find anyone better
than me; they're all dead.
Go to hell!
Okay! But l know the secret of
bell-making, and l won't tell.
What you saying?
l know the secret. My father knew
the secret of bell making.
Before he died, he passed it to me.
No one else knows, except me.
My father died and passed
me the secret.
Shall we take him?
What secret?
Do you want the Prince
to flay us?
He's lying about the secret.
The worse for him!
-What ism your name?
-Boriska.
Come here!
Mount!
What about the hut?
Did you persuade him?
Shall we did here?
We can it here.
But it would be more convenient to
do it closer to the Bell-tower...
So that we won't have to drag this
heavy thing far.
Can't we dig here?
Let's do it here.
Mark it out.
Let's dig together, shall we?
We're bell-casters, not diggers.
Why should we be digging?
You know what my father said...
before he died?
''Bell-casters must dig the
casting-pit.''
l only understood that in my old age,''
he said, and died.
l don't know what Nikolka said, but
l'm not going to dig.
Call us when you need us.
Well?
Did you find it?
There is no need to look for it.
Here it is.
No, it's not the right clay.
-We always took it here.
-Then you are fools.
The clay is very good.
-Andreika, isn't the clay bad?
-Yes, it's bad.
You see? Come on.
We'll search until we
find good clay.
Stepan, perhaps we shouldn't
have done this.
Come on. Look what clay we
have found.
How hard we've worked, and now
we've found a new spot.
lt's not the right kind.
lt's the end of August, and we
have not found the clay yet.
Think about yourself.
l'm sorry for you.
l've managed all these years
without your pity.
Let's go back, Boriska.
l can't. l know that's not
the right clay.
Then what is right?
l know what is.
l don't need people like you.
l can manage without you.
l don't need such people!
Andreika!
Semyon!
l have found it!
Uncle Fyodor! l've found it!
The clay! Uncles Seymon!
Stepan!
We've found the good clay,
Here is the clay!
l have found the clay, Stepan!
Andreika! Andreika!
Where are you all?
Boriska! Boriska!
-What?
-Shall l dig in?
l'm coming.
What are you saying?
l'm coming!
Where's Nikolai?
He left this morning
to fetch wood.
-lt should be here already.
-He'll be back by evening.
The evening? l need to
reinforce it now.
To the devil with your Nikolai,
he's an idiot.
Why are you standing there?
Work!
-The merchants don't agree.
-What do you mean?
They have tripled the price.
They say it's still cheap.
But it. What else can we do?
But it at this price?
Buy, l say!
The Prince will flay you.
We'll ruin him.
l no longer care. Buy it.
You're in the way, Father.
It's dangerous.
Don't dig in without me.
-Boriska!
-Just one moment.
The cast won't hold; it needs
another layer.
Another layer? You should have
applied the clay already.
You haven't put up the frame yet!
lt needs reinforcing, but there
are no more twigs.
We're not going to reinforce it.
We start firing tonight.
ls he kidding?
,
If we don't reinforce the cast
it won't hold.
lt will crack and our work
will be wasted.
,
If it with snows and we can't fire
won't our work be wasted, too?
They'll flog me, not you.
The cast won't hold like this.
Apply the clay.
Do you hear me?
l won't do it.
You won't Then get out!
Andreika, apply the clay.
He won't do it, either.
Are you going to apply the clay?
The metal will burst the mold.
lt needs reinforcement.
Will you obey me? Who is in
charge here?
lt needs reinforcement.
Fyodor!
Flog him! He refuses to work.
He won't obey my orders.
l'll show you who's in charge!
Your father treated us better.
You remember him? Then flog him
in my father's name.
All right, apply the clay.
Start the work without me.
But we're waiting for you.
Start without me.
Rest, sleep a little.
Why are you staring at me?
Lost your tongue? Are you deaf?
Are you sorry for him?
Go and console him; that's
what a monk is for.
O Lord. O Queen of Heaven...
l can't understand how the Grand
Prince trusted him with all this.
Boriska! Wake up!
l've started the firing.
Why did you start without me?
l told you to wake me.
Only know when to start.
Fyodor, the Prince's men have come,
and they want to see you.
What heat!
That's enough.
Not enough sliver; tell the Prince
not be so miserly.
Out Grand Prince is
never miserly.
l don't care. l need another
eighteen pounds of sliver.
What's eighteen pounds of sliver,
more or less?
Who knows the secret of
bell-casting, l or you?
Tell the Prince not to be
miserly. We need...
another sixteen pounds.
Are you mad?
l'll get all the silver l want
from the Prince.
lmagine, if after this it
doesn't ring!
Watch out.
l recognize him!
Beat him! Beat him!
Are you mad? To attack
someone like that.
You've mistaken him for another.
l'm not mistaken. l recognize
you, Judas.
How handsome he used to be then.
Now he has lost his looks.
Thanks to him, l spent ten
years in prison...
and they cut off half my tongue.
l'll kill him!
He's innocent, brother. He's
betrayed no one.
l swear by the Holy Cross. Lord,
why this punishment?
Strike me, but don't touch him.
Get up.
You're heavy.
The Prince's jester died.
They wanted me to go, but l'd
rather be a carpenter.
l recognize him.
He denounced me.
Give me something to drink.
There are worse things than that.
Andreika, stand aside.
Why stand there? Work!
OO Add some more,...
add some more!
Come on!
Boriska, where is he?
Boriska, the second
furnace is ready.
Go, go! We're all ready.
Open!
Everything is ready.
Shall we begin?
Come on!
lt's coming, Boriska! It's coming!
It's coming.
God, help me.
What a day tomorrow will be!
We should get some sleep.
Boriska! Let's go, shall we?
Just a moment.
This is what happened, Andrei.
l've thought it over and l've
decided to tell you.
You know how much l envied.
Envy just gnawed at me.
lt was inside me like a poison.
l couldn't stand it any longer,
that's why l left.
l left because of you.
When l heard you had given up
painting, the envy went.
My heart grew lighter.
Then l forgot.
l only want to copy the
Scriptures before l die.
The Father Superior is strict...
and his punishment is not easy
in my old age.
l'm afraid l won't have enough
time to finish my task.
Why am l repenting? Why should
l repent to you?
You yourself are a greater
sinner than l.
Yes, yes, greater than l.
What am l? A humble worm;
nothing is demanded of me.
But you, what are you?
For what sacred deed did God
give you your talent?
Lord, l don't want to say this.
l know Nikon has sent a third
messenger to you...
to persuade you to come back
to paint the Trinity.
And you sent them all back. You
wouldn't even talk to them.
l'll tell you the truth. l won't lie.
Then, in my dirty soul, there,
in the very depth of it...
there was a tiny flicker of joy.
And now...
my life is ending; my soul
calls out for rest.
Nikon doesn't care a bit
for you life.
He wants you here, to glorify and
strengthen his power with your talent.
Never mind Nikon, but
listen to me.
Go to the Trinity cathedral and
paint, paint, paint!
Don't burden your soul, for it is an
awful sin to deny the divine spark.
lf Theophanes were alive, wouldn't
he say the same thing?
Look at me, look at the ungifted one.
Why do you think l returned?
For a crust of bread, to finish my
life in peace.
l shall die soon and nothing will
remain after me.
And l know that l will die soon.
Nor have you much longer to live.
Do you want to take your
talent to the grave?
Why are you silent, Andrei? Give
me at me at least one word.
lt was l who denounced
that jester then.
Curse me, but don't stay
silent, Andrei.
Curse me.
Well, how is it?
Come on, then.
Everyone, get away!
What's going on up there?
Everything is okay.
Come on, come on!
Everyone go up!
Well? Come on.
Go on. Give the signal.
Come on!
The Grand Prince is coming with
a foreign ambassador.
ls everything ready?
lf not, watch out!
Motherfucker!
We bless and consecrate this
bell with holy water.
ln the name of the Father, Son
and Holy Ghost. Amen.
Look what kind of people are
overseeing here.
Where are you going?
lsn't rather peculiar?
They're all peculiar here.
Come on, come on, dumbbell!
Shall l help you, or will you
touch it yourself?
What do you think will come out
of all this travesty?
What do you think?
ln my opinion, nothing good
will come out of this.
Excuse me, Your Excellency,
but l think you are...
being deceived by appearances.
Look at all of this!
What do you think of this dumb
bell, this awkward scaffold?
l would sum it up and say this
bell will not ring.
ln fact, it can't ring.
Does Your Excellency wish
to make a wager?
l think you underestimate
the situation these...
people are in.
Besides, they were the
ones that built it.
That may be true, but l wouldn't
venture to call that thing a bell.
Excellency, they fully
understand...
That the Prince will behead them
if it doesn't ring.
Judging from the face
of that youth...
one could say that he is aware
of the circumstances.
Don't you think so?
Excellency...
Have you heard that the Grand
Prince beheaded his brother?
lt seems they were twins.
Look at that marvelous girl!
My God!
My friend, that girl is not more
than thirteen years old.
That doesn't make her
Iess attractive.
Sometimes these girls are
women at the thirteen.
What's the matter with you,
Your Excellency?
Come on, come on.
My father, that old snake, didn't
pass on the secret.
He died without telling me, he took
it to the grave. Skinflint scoundrel!
You see, it's turned
out very well.
Come on, come on.
Let's go together, you and l.
You'll cast bells.
l'll paint icons.
We'll go to the Trinity
Monastery together.
What a feast day for
the people.
You've brought them such joy,
and you're crying.
Come on, come on.
subtitles - sonicalchemy